Ahh, the machine riding Nora with the special spear.
How lucky to come across you.
I have a proposal.
Come closer.
Call me Fernund.
Hey, Fernund, my eyes are up here.
I'm looking at your spear.
It's magnificent.
But how does it work?
You stick the pointy end into the machine.
Yes, but, how does it turn foe into friend?
It's simple really.
Yes?
You wouldn't understand.
What's your proposal?
During the reign of that idiot Carja king
outlanders often hid items of value from raiders.
Well, I found one.
What is it?
A relic from the Old Ones.
You probably would understand it better than I do.
Unfortunately, it's too high for me to reach.
Uh-huh, and you want me to get it for you?
What a brilliant plan!
You're a much better climber than I am, to be sure.
Get it, bring it back, and we'll split the proceeds.
How about I see what it is first?
That works too.
What do you do exactly?
I'm a trader of fine tinkerings. I buy low, sell high.
But in this case, you wouldn't be buying.
Sometimes I "find" tinkerings as well.
Let's say I'm interested.
What do I need to do?
The relic rests on the rise of Dusk Mesa.
Bring it to me at the Meridian docks and we will both profit.
Leave me alone, girl.
Can't you see I'm searching the water?
Okay. What's wrong? Has someone fallen in?
No.
Have you seen a girl of about seventeen?
I can't even say it.
Are you afraid she jumped to her death?
I don't know!
Elida, my only daughter, she's gone!
Who else is searching for her?
I demanded the guards look for her,
but I can't put my hope in them.
They say girls run off all the time at this age.
Not my Elida.
I've reached out to her friends.
But they say they haven't seen her in weeks.
Weeks!
How could I not know?
I've searched everywhere.
And then I thought maybe she might be…
…here, in the water.
Has she done or said anything unusual?
She's been like a different person.
She used to be such a happy girl,
playing in the dirt with the boys.
What changed?
I don't know.
She disagrees with me about everything.
Hates the ceasefire.
Thinks we never should have fought the war to begin with.
It's been a month since I've seen her smile,
she spends so much time in her room.
I should have paid more attention.
Did something happen during the war that upset her?
The war upset us all.
The cruelty, the Mad Sun-King, the blood on the streets.
When Itamen's men fled, they stormed through here.
There's a ceasefire now, of course,
but Elida broods about it more than ever.
It bothers her that our people are so divided.
I'm a good tracker, I could look for her.
Where did you last see her?
Just last night, in the house.
She seemed better.
Was she ill?
She seemed withdrawn.
Sad.
So I was pleased when she wanted to go out in the garden.
That's the last I saw of her.
I'll do my best.
May the Sun light your way.
[Carja guard]
Move along, you have no need to loiter around here.
I'm awake, and alert.
Looks like Elida left a few things behind.
Aren't these for spying far away?
[Carja merchant]
You won't find better wares.
What's in this bottle?
I guess she was doing some gardening.
Ugh, it smells like ash or rotten eggs.
Better pour that out.
Why would you need a spyglass in the garden?
Something buried.
No, something dug up.
Must have left a trail.
[Carja guard]
Some Oseram girl applied to the city guard the other day. Amazing.
[Carja merchant]
Buy what you need, leave the rest.
[Carja villager]
You should be proud of what you've done for us.
Flower petals.
Why would she take flowers from her own garden?
[Lahavis]
Did you find anything in the garden?
Nothing definite yet. I'll let you know.
[Carja merchant]
Would you like to buy something today?
[Carja villager]
Dervahl stormed the palace and still he lives?
[Carja merchant]
Buy what you need, leave the rest.
Don't pass up on these goods.
[Carja villager]
He tried to kill the Sun-King, unbelievable!
The petals end here, at the water.
Could her father have been right, but at the wrong place?
Ropes to tie up a boat that isn't here.
Maybe she took the boat to that island over there.
Looks like I'm in for a long swim.
Save these for the trail.
The boat, this looks promising.
Calm, calm.
Is that you?
You did it!
Who are you?
How did you learn to fight like that?
What are you doing on this island?
I come here to be alone.
Do you know your father fears you're dead?
Huh, I'm surprised he even noticed I was gone.
He has the whole village looking for you.
He's worried.
The Snapmaw kept me.
You took care of it, so thank you.
I should be fine now.
Why did you bring flowers here?
No real reason.
I'm trying to make this a place for us.
For all of us.
Who's "us"?
Is there someone else here?
No. No!
I was going to surprise my friends with what I made.
There's no one else here, obviously.
Let's go back to the village together.
I need to finish planting my garden.
Just a little more time.
I'll be fine, I promise.
You know, I think I'll take a little more time too, to look around.
You don't need to do that.
I really do.
Bedrools. Two of them.
And a set of cups.
She must not have been alone here.
Looks like Elida has a friend.
Elida, if you came here to be alone, why are there two bedrolls?
And don't lie to me this time.
Um, uh…
…by the Sun, I don't know where he is!
Who?
Atral.
He lights a fire signal when it's safe to meet him.
But he's not here.
Who's Atral?
A friend I've known since childhood.
I'd be planting in the garden
and he'd dump worms down my back.
I hated that.
But the last few months we'd meet here and…
…everything was different.
We talked for hours.
He help me plant that garden.
I couldn't wait to see him again.
It's like I'm dead and only come alive when I'm here with him.
Do you know what that's like?
I can't say that I do.
Atral is a soldier for the Carja in Shadow,
stationed at the outpost across the lake.
It's treason for us to even meet.
How could I tell my father?
How could I tell anyone?
Well, then, how did you two arrange to meet here?
We came here as kids.
After he left, I would come back sometimes.
One day I surprised him here.
He smiled from ear to ear.
We sat and played like we had his kids, but…
The war had changed him.
Changed us both.
We weren't kids any more.
We started meeting in secret.
He'd light a fire to signal it was safe for him
to leave his post at the citadel, but…
…last night…
He didn't come?
I've been waiting all night and all day.
I haven't seen anyone but you.
Enough of this, you have to go back.
Please, if you came all this way will you look for Atral?
He lit the fire on the island not far from here.
If I go… he could be killed!
We could break the cease fire.
But a Nora wouldn't.
I didn't mean for any of this to happen, I'm so sorry.
I'll find him if I can, as long as you go home to your father.
I will.
Please come find me there.
I can't sleep.
I can't breathe knowing Atral could be out there, hurting.
Here's what's left of the fire.
Looks like some sort of scuffle.
Ending with someone being dragged away.
[distant cries of pain]
[in the distance]
Hey, speak up or I'll cut off the other finger.
Who were you signalling?
[cries of pain]
That must be Atral!
[Shadow Carja soldier]
Sick of hearing him scream, wanna hear him talk.
[Aloy]
Quite a few guards there.
[Shadow Carja soldier]
Hard to believe that thing fought alongside us.
[Aloy]
Maybe there's another way in?
[Shadow Carja soldier]
I tell ya, traitors are everywhere.
I don't know about that.
[Shadow Carja soldier]
Sure, soon as it gets a little hard, people give up.
Wanna do the easy thing instead of the right thing.
[Shadow Carja soldier]
Listen to him.
Doesn't sound easy. He's been at it for hours.
[Shadow Carja soldier]
I guarantee he lit that fire to signal his Meridian pals to come and save him.
Sit back in the capital. Easy as you please.
[Shadow Carja soldier]
Hear they've got plenty of food over there.
So what if they do? Doesn't make 'em right.
[Shadow Carja soldier]
No monstrous darkness should keep us f…
Never seen a man take a beating like that, and he still won't talk.
Let's do this!
[Shadow Carja soldier]
Got someone to fight here.
Don't let me die.
[Shadow Carja soldier]
The word of Shadow…
Gonna make you pay for that.
[Shadow Carja soldier]
Take the fight to them, you miserable chuff!
That hurt!
[Shadow Carja soldier]
Let this deliver the final blow!
I'm down!
[Shadow Carja soldier]
Stay in shadow!
Calm…
[Shadow Carja soldier]
Look out, someone's up there.
…war, chasing rats.
[Shadow Carja soldier]
Help me, fools!
I'm broke, bad.
[Shadow Carja soldier]
Vanished like a blasted Stalker.
Atral!
Elida sent me.
Elida.
I was gonna ask her to leave with me, to go into the outlands.
Summer out in the sun where no shadow could reach us.
But we wouldn't have made it.
They would have followed me.
I know now.
Elida!
Tell her they never learned about our island.
She's safe.
Give her this.
Tell her it's worth it.
Poor Atral.
And poor Elida.
[Carja]
- Fish like my new lure, made it from a Grazer coil.
- You'll like what I have for sale, I promise.
[Carja merchants]
- These aren't goods, they're necessities!
- You won't find better wares.
[Carja guard]
Words to live by.
[Carja villager]
Could've sworn the other stall was down here. Oh well.
[Carja merchants]
- Check out these wares.
- I've got all the best goods here.
[Carja merchant]
I've got all the best goods here.
[Carja guard]
Some Oseram girl applied to the…
Those damn Oseram, stirring up tensions. Keeping my eyes on them.
Elida came back!
She hugged me, said she loved me.
But now she just sits in the garden like she's waiting.
Waiting for what?
Something's not right.
Maybe you could talk to her?
I'll, uh, do my best.
Don't say it.
I know he's gone.
The Shadow Carja found him.
But you should know he never betrayed you.
He wanted you to have this key.
It's a key to the lock he gave me.
He said our lives were locked together.
Thank you for bringing it back
For all you did for us.
He said it was worth it.
All of it.
Are you all right?
No.
I can't imagine how you're feeling, but you don't have to go it alone.
Your father was crushed when he thought you were dead.
Crushed!
He still treats me like a perfect doll.
His prized possession.
No, with Atral gone, I'm all alone.
It isn't worth it.
Wait, Elida.
I was wrong about what Atral said.
He didn't say it was worth it.
He said it is worth it.
All of it.
Our losses can feel overwhelming.
But they remind us of our connections to others.
To Atral, even to your father.
Atral would have wanted you to remember that, and go on.
I know it.
Now, will you?
I…
I'll try.
Please, let me get your father.
Will you talk to him?
I guess.
I should have given you a token for your kindness in finding Elida.
Is something wrong?
Elida needs you to listen, right now.
Go to the garden, quickly.
Uh, I will, at once.
[Carja guard]
Watch out for the Oseram merchants, they'll as soon cheat you as look at you.
There are no shadows under the noonday Sun, words to live by.
[Elida]
It's about Atral, father. He and I were together.
[Lahavis]
Atral? Yes, I remember him.
From when you two are no taller than the flowers in your mother's garden.
But, he went west.
They never found out about us.
He didn't tell them.
Even when they…
Oh Elida, all that time spent writing edicts, I thought…
I thought my work was keeping you safe from this war.
It was all just parchment.
And I could have lost you.
I'm so sorry, Father.
I wish I'd known all this time what you were going through.
But we'll…
…I'll be better.
Thank you for this second chance.
[Carja guard]
Machines or bandits try to get past me, they'll have a fight. Mark my words.
Arrested two for disorderly conduct last night.
[Carja guard]
You don't want to know what they were doing.
[Carja villager]
Oseram scum, sending killers after the Sun-King.
I bet those traitorous Oseram…
[Carja villager]
You're in for a treat, it's quite a show.
[Carja guard]
Always stay bright, always stay alert. That's what I say.